Leah: If a child or young person seems
to be depressed, it's important to
talk to them, to try to find out what's
troubling them and how they're feeling.
Whatever is causing the problem,
it should be taken seriously.
But first we need to know that there
is something wrong, and how to identify
the signs or symptoms of ‘Depression’
in children and young people.
Let’s look at some of the signs
and symptoms of depression
in children and young people.
Rhiannon: Feeling sad, in a low
mood that doesn’t go away, or being
irritable or grumpy all the time.
Constantly feeling tired,
sleeping more than usual or maybe
having trouble sleeping all.
Interacting less with friends
and family and not being
interested in things in general.
Eating less than usual or overeating
and having big changes in weight.
Unable to relax or being more lethargic
than usual or unable to feel emotions.
Lacking confidence or talking
about feeling worthless.
Self-harming, or even
talking about suicide.
Leah: We can see from these signs and
symptoms that depression and anxiety which
we have looked at previously are very
similar in the way the present themselves.
This is because some children and
young people with anxiety also
develop depression and vice versa.
Rhiannon: If children or young people
are resistant to discussing their
feelings or admitting that they may be
depressed, they should be encouraged
to talk to someone they trust, such as
a family member, a friend or someone
at school or should see their GP and
or be referred to specialist services.